Welcome to the centrifuge where we
separate the nonsense from the
sciencebacked claims across health
shows. In this episode, I'd like to get
into some claims made by Dr. Robert
Lustig on the Hubertman podcast. Dr.
Lustik is a professor of pediatrics and
endocrinology and has a practice and
work related to childhood obesity and
diabetes. In this episode, Dr. Listik
covers a number of topics that we will
dive into. Here they are. A calorie
eaten is not a calorie eaten. Amino
acids from protein are used differently
based on your circumstance. The unique
properties of omega-3s and trans fats,
glucose, sugar being vital for life. And
finally, fructose sugar is addictive.
This will be a pretty lengthy one, so
I'll supply timestamps and I'll offer
you a summary at the of the most
important points at the end. Studies
I'll be referencing are also attached
for you. Let's spin it. Well, I think
people are very interested in what to
eat, what not to eat. And we'll start
off simply talking about what most
everyone believes and understands, which
is that a calorie is a form of heat
energy
that's given off during the processing
of some food bit or something. If that's
mysterious to people, just understand
that a calorie is a unit of energy.
And I was taught and still many many
people worldwide believe that a calorie
is a calorie. Meaning if I consume more
calories in whatever form then I
metabolize by thinking, feeling, moving,
exercising etc. then I will gain weight.
And if I consume fewer calories than I
burn, I will lose weight. And we could
talk a lot about where that weight loss
comes from. Does it come from atapost
body fat stores or from muscle or from
protein or muscle of course is protein
etc. But let's start off with is a
calorie truly a calorie when it comes to
the processing of different types of
calories. Everyone thinks that obesity
is about energy balance
that is calories in calories out.
Therefore, two behaviors, gluttony and
sloth. Therefore, if you're fat, it's
your fault. Therefore,
diet and exercise. Therefore, any
calorie can be part of a balanced diet.
Therefore, don't pick on our calories.
Go pick on somebody else's calories.
This is actually what the food industry
uses to assuage their culpability for
the change in the food supply and the
rise in obesity and chronic disease like
diabetes. Now it is true that a calorie
is that unit of energy that raises one
gram of water one degree centigrade. And
so therefore a calorie burned is a
calorie burned. I don't argue that.
That's true. That's, you know, the first
law of thermodynamics.
>> Let me jump in here and quickly
acknowledge Dr. Lustik's point about a
calorie being a calorie. I've been
fighting this fight for quite some time.
So, I completely agree with him here.
Often times, we confuse nutrients or
foods as the same when we're simply
discussing the caloric value of those
foods, which can be the same even if the
foods are not. I would likely con
contextualize that that not everyone
simplifies it down to calories in
calories out being the cause of obesity.
Yes, this is the necessary foundation
for obesity to occur. But the reason for
the imbalance in calories is
acknowledged in the literature as
multiaceted. It's not like all the obese
people are simply lazy, gluttony, and
sloth as Dr. Listik is illustrating it.
Maybe to many people who aren't educated
on the topic, it could be argued that
way. But most researchers in the field
would take a more understanding and
multiffactorial approach to describe the
mechanisms of overconumption. For
example, in some scientific reviews,
researchers point out that metabolism
i.e. the sloth aspect or caloric
expenditure side of equation can slow
down to weight loss itself through
hormonal changes, literal body mass
changes and more. Now, a concept called
metabolic adaptation. If some people
have more of this adaptation that puts
them at a disadvantage when losing body
fat and researchers also offer different
models to explain the adaptations of
metabolism, for example, like the set
point model, the settling point model,
and the static model. The point here is
researchers are unlikely to blame
obesity merely on the lack of physical
activity and overconumption due to
gluttony. There are many physiological
factors that contribute to this accepted
imbalance in calories and similar
calories and foods does not make the
foods equal in their physiological
impact. But that doesn't mean a calorie
eaten is a calorie eaten.
[clears throat]
That's not the same. And that's where
people get it wrong. So let me give you
some examples of how that calorie eaten
is not a calorie eaten.
You like almonds? I do.
>> Me, too. Almonds are great. Okay. You
eat 160 calories in almonds.
How many of those do you absorb?
130.
You eat 160, you absorb 130. Where' the
other 30 go in the processing of that
food energy? No.
Turned out the fiber in those almonds,
both soluble and insoluble fiber. And by
the way, fiber is sort of the key to the
kingdom in this story.
Forms a gel on the inside of your
intestine. The insoluble fiber, the
cellulose, forms a fishnet, if you will,
a lattice work on the inside of your
dadum. The soluble fiber, which are
globular, plug the holes in that
fishnet. Together, they form a secondary
barrier. You can actually see it on
electron microscopy, a whitish gel. And
that prevents absorption of those 30
calories. So yes, 130 get absorbed, but
many of them don't. They end up going
further down the intestine to the next
part called the junum, and that's where
the microbiome is. Now, everyone knows
about the microbiome nowadays. You know,
it's all the bacteria. You know, we
always say when women are pregnant,
you're eating for two. Well, we're
always eating for 100 trillion.
Now they have to eat. Well, what do they
eat? They eat what you eat. The question
is, how much did you get versus how much
did they get? Well, if you ate almonds,
they're getting those 30 calories. So,
even though you count the calories at
your lips,
that doesn't matter. What really matters
is counting the calories at your
intestinal brush border.
Okay? And they're not the same. So, if
you feed your gut, that's a good thing
because then your gut will take those
calories and turn it into things like
short- chain fatty acids which end up
being protective against chronic
metabolic disease, acetate, propionate,
butyrate, valerate. Those are actually
good. They're anti-inflammatory,
anti-Alzzheimer's
because you fed your microbiome.
So, even though you ate 160, you
absorbed 130. So a calorie eaten is not
a calorie eaten because if you ate it
with fiber, it wasn't for you. It was
for your bacteria. But that's not the
way you count them up. So that's problem
number one. Okay. So here we're
beginning to discuss the concept of a
calorie eaten is not a calorie eaten.
Dr. Listic is using an almond example,
which is perfect because we have studies
on almonds and their absorption compared
to the stated energy values. So the
calorie value. In this study,
participants were fed a controlled
amount of almonds with a controlled
meal. And then researchers measured the
amount of energy calories remained in
their fecal matter, their poop. If we
have 100% absorption, we'd expect no
calorie containing nutrients to be
found. But when measuring the fecal
matter, you can see at the very bottom
that calorie rich nutrients were still
found with more in the almond consuming
groups. This means that Dr. istic is
absolutely right that the calories
consumed as food are not perfectly
absorbed. So the actual amount of
calories containing nutrients absorbed
in the bloodstream and used in our cells
is sometimes less than what we measured
at the nutrition label. The reason for
that could be multiple reasons in fact
one of them is immediately described by
Dr. Listik as fiber. So fiber which we
saw is also excreted more in the almond
condition can definitely interfere with
the absorption shown in many studies. We
see images like this of the intestinal
wall. It's tough to see but those are
microvilli after exposure to fiber and
they've expanded slightly as a reaction
to the fiber. The point here is that
fiber changes the absorption of calorie
metabolizable nutrients which changes
the energy actually extracted from the
food even if the calorie value the
energy value is higher on the food
label. And that's not even considering
Dr. Lustig's point about the microbiome
and how it will also take up fiber and
convert it to different fats. The me the
ones that he mentioned several so like
butyrate propionate and so on. Now,
these fats can then be taken up by the
colon cells and used for energy or
passed on to the liver and other cells
of the body. And while I won't go
disease by disease on their effects
here, they have generally recognized as
a net positive for our overall health,
some of which I've covered in the past.
This all comes together to give a thumbs
up to Dr. Lustik's points. He's spoton,
especially about the intricacies of it
all. I'll be discussing all of this in
more depth at the end because there's
some actionable steps on how to use this
information that I'd like to touch on.
Problem number two, amino acids. So, we
all eat protein.
Let's say you eat too much protein. You
have, you know, the porterhouse steak.
All right? Now, if you're a bodybuilder,
those amino acids might go to muscle and
you might increase your muscle mass
because you're a bodybuilder because
you're putting uh excess uh force on
those muscles and you're growing those
muscles. Okay? But let's say you're not
a bodybuilder. Let's say you're a mere
mortal like me
>> or let's say you're a kid going through
puberty who's synthesizing a lot of
muscle not because they're lifting
weights, because they're
>> because testosterone is making it
happen. Yeah, absolutely. But let's say
you're not. Let's say, you know, you're
just, you know, just sch slump off the
the street like uh, you know, Joe Mo,
okay? And you eat that porter house.
You've taken on all these amino acids.
There's no place to store it other than
muscle. So your liver takes the excess
and deamidates that amino acid, takes
the amino group off to turn it from a
amino acid into an organic acid. And
then that organic acid can then enter
the KB cycle, the triaroxyic acid cycle.
What goes on in the mitochondria in
order to generate ATP, the chemical
energy that your body needs in order to
power itself. Okay, now that's a good
thing. It takes double the amount of
energy to prepare that amino acid for
burning as it does to uh prepare a
carbohydrate for burning
>> or because when I asked about when you
asked about almonds why the the 160
versus 130 I thought it was the
processing and turned out it was fiber.
You're saying for protein let's let's
make it realistic for a a really nice
big porter house steak which I love by
the way. Let's say let's say 800
calories.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, it turns out
>> how how much of that is is uh so that's
what goes in your mouth,
>> right?
>> My mouth,
>> How much of it is actually um eaten in
uh to stay with the your calorie eaten
is not a calorie eaten in the processing
of that? What percentage is actually
goes into your total caloric intake?
>> Right? So about 10% of everything you
eat goes to just maintaining body
temperature. It's called the thermic
effect of food. But when you're eating
protein, you actually generate more
heat. And the reason is because it takes
two ATP to phosphorolate that organic
acid as opposed to one ATP to uh
phosphorolate that carbohydrate for uh
consumption. So you actually have a net
loss of energy because it was a an amino
acid versus a monossaccharide, a sugar.
Now you you brought up fat. Fat doesn't
need to be phosphorolated. So it
actually doesn't have any um thermic
effect of food at that point. So depends
on what it is as to whether or not you
have loss. The next example put forward
by Dr. istic is the idea that the amino
acids that you consume from proteins are
actually used differently based on your
circumstance like being a bodybuilder
versus being sedentary. Now here again
he brings up a good point because the
building block molecules that make up
the proteins that we consume called
amino acids do get integrated into our
body differently like if you're
exercising or not. So scientists use
tracer experiments where they literally
follow the same amino acids consumed in
exercising versus non-ex exercising
individuals as these amino acids travel
through the bloodstream. Then they can
trace if the amino acids because these
amino acids have been tagged are
integrated into the muscle tissue or
not. This means that they're then used
differently if there are differences
between the two groups. Ultimately, this
tells us that amino acids are likely not
metabolized equally. They do depend on
circumstance. Now, another point is that
amino acids need to be converted to
usable molecules for energy. These
molecules that they are converted to
then enter the mitochondrian, that old
powerhouse of the cell, which then
converts them to usable cellular energy.
This whole process requires energy
input, making proteins less efficient to
be metabolized for energy. When Dr.
istic is discussing phosphorilation.
He's saying that the cells of your body
are taking the cellular energy molecules
adenosine triphosphate so ATP that your
mitochondria produce and taking a
phosphate off of that energy molecule
ATP and applying it to the amino acids
once they've been converted to an
intermediate molecule. Now, he argues
that creates a net loss of energy
because carbohydrates like glucose take
one ATP as opposed to two that amino
acids do. Frankly, we're getting pretty
into the weeds with the biochemistry
here. So, this applicably makes almost
no difference, but he's somewhat
incorrect here as some amino acids
produce the same net amount of ATP as
glucose molecules do. Now I'm saying
some because it depends on the amino
acids. Some enter the mitochondrian at
different stages of metabolism making
some amino acids more or less efficient
at producing cellular energy. So i.e.
this ATP than glucose. I'm going to stop
there because this is a massive nerdy
rabbit hole that won't serve you. If you
want to hear a bit more about the
nuances then check out my extended
insider version of this video. If we
zoom out and focus in on the thermic
effect of food, which is the metabolism
expenditure that we experience from
simply eating food, regardless of all
the biochemical pathways and the yields
of ATP, which we can actually put aside,
it is true that protein causes a greater
thermic effect of food. So your
metabolism, calories expended, used will
likely be greater by eating protein.
That is because as Dr. istic also
pointed out that the preparation of
amino acids for energy production or the
synthesis of new functional proteins
within our muscles and other processes
to be honest simply cost more energy
with protein. The point here isn't for
you to memorize all the differences
between the amino acids. The point is to
simply acknowledge that the final energy
yield relative to carbohydrates varies
depending on which amino acid that
you're discussing. In addition, yes, the
direct impact of protein on metabolism
is greater than for the other nutrients,
carbohydrates or fats. Now, before we
continue, let me acknowledge that this
can get pretty deep into the murky
waters of physiology and biochemistry.
Here's the good news. You don't need to
know any of it to create actionable
steps for yourself. This is more so an
exercise in teasing out what is correct
and what needs tweaking. At the end,
I'll have some things to say on how to
easily think about all of this and how
to apply it. Don't worry.
>> Now, let's take the third. Let's take
fats. So, over here we have omega-3s,
heart healthy, anti-inflammatory,
anti-alzheimer's, save your life. And
over here we have trans fats, the devil
incarnate, consumable poison, because
you can't break the transdouble bond.
you don't have the desaturates to break
that trans double bond. So, it basically
accumulates, lines your arteries, lines
your liver, causes chronic metabolic
disease, causes insulin resistance.
Omega-3s
don't even get broken down for energy
because they're so important. They stay
intact because your brain needs them,
your heart needs them.
Whereas trans fats can't be broken down
because of that transdouble bond. One
save your life, other one kill you.
They're both nine calories per gram if
you explode them in a bomb calorimeter
because a calorie burned is a calorie
burned. But a calorie eaten is not a
calorie eaten because one will save your
life, one will kill you. Dr. Lustik is
getting into the differences between
fats. He focuses in on trans fats and
omega-3 fats. These are both unsaturated
fats, meaning that they have a kink in
the structure of the fat. That's
important to know because he mentions
that trans fats are highly damaging and
overall destructive to health because
they can't be metabolized. The reason
that kink that he calls a double bond
that can't be removed and therefore the
fat can't be metabolized.
Now this is a bit puzz puzzling because
he mentions that we don't have the
enzyme called desaturates to break the
double bond. Again that's the kink in
the structure of the fat. However,
desaturates enzymes do the opposite.
They introduce double bonds not take
them away. Either way, let's assume a
slip, which everyone has. It is also
incorrect to say that we can't
metabolize trans fats as there are
studies testing that very question and
reporting convincingly that trans fats
like those in industrial processing can
be metabolized. Unfortunately, Dr.
Listik also misses the mark on omega-3
fats. The body does use them as
signaling molecules and they're related
to many positive health outcomes, but
they are also metabolized for energy as
well. We see that in human studies as
well. So for this section, Dr. Lustik
gets a lot wrong. But in the overall
points, trans fats are negative to
health and omega-3s are net positive.
He's certainly correct. In the end, the
takeaway here is to avoid trans fats and
focus on omega-3 fats. There's more that
I could say, but let's move on. In fact,
I know that we've covered a lot, but if
you're looking for a deeper dive on all
the studies referenced so far, like the
experiments on trans fats or fiber or
more on the mechanisms of amino acid
metabolism and much more, consider the
extended version of this video. If you
can stomach it, that is the extended
version is included for the Physionic
Insider members along with accompanying
article, a shortened summary, and I'll
even send an email your way every week
as I do with all my analyses. running
past must be a hundred health topics
analyzed and increasing every week.
Plus, you'll get all these perks right
over here. It's a steal, I tell you. The
link to join the insiders is in the
description. Hope to speak with you over
there. All right, so glucose fructose.
Glucose is the energy of life. Every
cell on the planet burns glucose for
energy. Glucose is so damn important
that if you don't consume it, your body
makes it. So, it will take an amino acid
and turn it into glucose. That's
gluconneioenesis.
>> Gluconioenesis. That's right. It will
take a fatty acid and turn it into
glucose. And specifically the glycerol
portion of the uh triglyceride will turn
into glucose.
So
the inuit
they didn't have any place to grow
carbohydrate. They had ice. They had
whale blubber. They still had a serum
glucose level. And the reason is because
you had to you have to have a serum
glucose level in order to power your
brain, in order to power your heart.
Yes, you you can use ketones. Of course,
you can, but you know, only if you're in
a ketogenic state will you use
exclusively ketones. And you also need
glucose for structural changes in
specific proteins and particularly
hormones. So glucose molecules will stud
TSH, LH, FSH, different pituitary
hormones in order to increase their
potency. It's one of the reasons why
aging leads to defective hormonogenesis.
For instance, hypogonatism,
hypothyroidism is the loss of
glycosillation on individual um uh uh
peptide hormones because of uh the
inability to add glucose because insulin
>> no just it's an aging phenomenon.
>> Okay, now we enter the realm of
carbohydrates.
Dr. istic is discussing how critical
glucose, a carbohydrate, also known as a
monossaccharide, is to our survival, and
he's spot on. The reality is if we don't
have glucose in our blood, we fall into
a coma and die quickly. No ands, ifs, or
buts. He then mentions the need for
glucose molecules to stud hormones. This
is known as postransational
modifications. After a protein is
produced into a mature form like a
hormone, it underos further processing
or maturation by having modifications
made to it inside a compartment of the
cell called the endopplasmic reticulum.
One of those modifications is called
glycosillation and it involves the
attachment of glucose molecules. Without
it, the hormone or protein is less
functional. It's definitely important
like Dr. Listik mentions. The main point
here being that your blood sugar is
critical to your existence and your
hormones and other proteins aren't fully
functional in certain situations until
they've been modified further within
your cells through the attachment of
glucose molecules to those proteins.
Now, let's get into the big one,
fructose addiction.
Fructose on the other hand, this sweet
molecule, the molecule we seek, the
reason why the food industry studs every
food in the grocery store, you know, 73%
of all items in the American grocery
store have added sugar on purpose for
the food industry's purposes, not for
yours. Because fructose is addictive,
activates the nucleus, the reward center
of the brain in the same way that co
cocaine, heroin, nicotine, alcohol do
and drives dopamine receptors down just
like nicotine, you know, alcohol, you
know, cocaine, heroin do.
That molecule fructose is number one uh
completely vestigial to all vertebrate
life. There is no biochemical reaction
in any vertebrate that requires dietary
fructose. That's number one. Number two,
>> okay, sorry, I'm gonna just answer. So,
you're saying that even though we can
process fructose,
>> we have a limited capacity to process it
in the same way we have a limited
capacity to metabolize alcohol.
>> Now, if you have one drink a day, yeah,
you're okay. If you have two drinks a
day, depends on how big you are. You
know, you and I can probably
>> I would argue two drinks a week is the
maximum, but but let's not go there. The
um but but in terms of you're saying
when you say
fructose processing of fructose is
vestigial, what you're saying is that we
don't need to do it. It's like the
appendix. It's an organ for which it has
no function.
>> Exactly. And fructose has no function in
the human body.
>> Period.
>> You don't need it.
>> Don't need it. But our diet is replete
with it. In fact, our fructose
consumption's gone up 25fold
since the beginning of the last century.
I
>> I have to ask this now. I love fruit. I
eat
>> berries galore,
>> especially since the price of berries
seems to have come down. It used to be
that you only get them certain times a
year. I'm what you call a driveby
blueberry eater. So, I'll just walk past
and just take a fistful. You can't put
them in front of me without me eating
them. This is even difficult for me when
other people I don't know are eating
them. So,
>> um I eat lots of blueberries,
>> strawberries, blackberries if they're in
season. I love them.
>> No problem.
>> Loaded with fructose?
>> No.
>> Plenty of fiber. Low fructose.
>> Low fructose in berries. Berries are the
lowest fructose of all the
>> worried about asking you this today.
Thank you. Okay. Um
>> and fruit is okay because of the fiber.
So the molecule, the fructose molecule
is the same whether it's in a berry or
in an banana or for that matter in a
Coca-Cola. The fructose molecule is the
same molecule. The difference is that in
the berry it comes with a whole lot of
fiber. In the banana it comes with a
whole lot less fiber and in the
Coca-Cola it doesn't come with any
fiber. And the fiber is what mitigates
the absorption.
So when you consume the fructose with
fiber, so your blueberries, you're
feeding your microbiome, that fructose
wasn't for you.
>> The major claim here is that fructose is
addictive. Though some other points were
also brought up, too, like uh fructose
function in the body or that fruit is
fine, though it may also contain
fructose, and we'll get to those. First,
is fructose addictive and is it
addictive in the same way as cocaine?
This is a tough one to tease out for
multiple reasons. One, I don't have a
neurossychiatric background, so I'm not
educated on the detailed definitions of
addiction. Two, there aren't many
studies measuring addictive like
behavior with fructose, as far as I can
tell. Now, researchers in the field seem
to disagree with Dr. Lustik, saying that
there is insufficient evidence to
characterize anything related to sugar
addiction. In fact, they say there's
little to no evidence indicating that in
humans and what animal studies exist are
highly contextbased, as in after food
deprivation or intermittent access to
sugar, which can lead to binging. Then
when we look at cocaine research,
something Tony Montana might know a
thing or two about, researchers focus a
lot on the dopamine aspects, as in
reduced dopamine function. A common
brain molecule is involved in the
addiction cycle. Now, there are studies
using fructose that indicate dopamine
function is reduced with fructose
consumption. Now, behaviorally, there's
some evidence in humans that fructose
can lead to increased appetite compared
to glucose alone. Yet, when we compare
foods with no fructose to foods with
fructose, there's no additional
consumption of food when allowed to
consume unlimited food after exposure to
fructose or not. Now, this could be
because participants didn't have access
to foods containing fructose, like a
cocaine addict might want more cocaine.
However, there are studies that look at
that too indirectly. People drinking the
same amount of glucose, fructose, or
water only were then allowed to eat as
much as they wanted. And you would
expect that the fructose consumers would
eat more of the fructose containing
nutrients like the supplied cookies and
sugary drinks, but they didn't. They
actually ate the same amount as everyone
else, including the water condition. In
fact, the researchers even pointed this
out. They say it is noteworthy that
subjects ingesting 197 calories of
fructose showed almost perfect
regulation reducing food intake by about
225 calories relative to subjects who
had zero calorie preload of water. On
the other hand, subjects with the
glucose preload showed potentiation of
intake, leading to about 450 more
calories overall than the water subjects
after ingesting both the preload and the
buffet meal. So that means in this
study, the fructose consuming group had
better consumption regulation control
than the glucose condition, which is
antithetic to Dr. Listik's point. If I
can take a step back for a second and
look at the whole picture, it would take
a lot more detailed reading and analysis
of the literature to really tease out
the harm of fructose from a consumption
and and addiction perspective. But what
we can take away from this is that it is
highly unlikely that fructose is as
addictive as cocaine. It is also highly
unlikely that fructose is strongly
addictive in general. And finally, even
if it turned out that it was mildly
addictive, the effect is clearly so weak
that it is inconsistently found in human
studies. So, is it really something to
worry about? I would argue no. Then,
does fructose have a role in the body?
It actually does have a role in the
body. However, because our body produces
fructose, it is unnecessary to consume
in our diet. In addition, many of the
roles of fructose can also be handled
through other metabolic pathways like
glycogen synthesis, a storage form of
glucose molecules in our liver and
muscles. However, there is a unique role
of fructose in a strange place.
Men, listen up. Your sperm need
fructose. Specifically, the seinal
secretions contain large amounts of
fructose because fructose is used in
energy generation for the movement of
sperm. In fact, it may be preferred over
glucose which most other cells use. I'll
be honest, I did not know that. I
learned something new doing the
background research for this. However,
make no mistake, fructose consumption is
still unnecessary. Though there are
biochemical reactions, metabolic
pathways that use fructose molecule and
it does serve a limited purpose. It just
doesn't need to be consumed. It can be
produced within your body. Finally, what
about fruit? It contains fructose, but
as Dr. Lustik pointed out, it seems fine
simply because it's consumed in
combination with beneficial molecules
like the fiber that we discussed
earlier. This is a tough one to cover
because using terms like fruit is okay
is such a general expression. It really
just isn't defined. Like berries are
beneficial for reducing cardiovascular
disease risk. It's specific. So plenty
to say here, especially with so many
different fruits, but researchers
largely agree with Dr. Lustik as across
many studies, fruit consumption is
strongly related to many improved health
outcomes. There may be many reasons for
that which are beyond the scope of what
we're doing here, but no doubt fiber is
one of them to Dr. Lustik's point. Now,
we've covered a ton of material and in
truth all of these topics deserve deeper
dives as there's much more to say on
each. However, we can take some things
away from this instead of keeping it to
an intellectual exercise in critiquing
claims. First, I did promise to pull
some of these elements together into
some actionable takeaways. For example,
when we discuss a calorie eaten is not a
calorie eaten, or that certain amino
acids provide more energy than others,
or how fiber blocks our absorption, it
can seem pretty hopeless on how to
approach nutrition if there's just so
many factors at play all at once. So,
here's how I think about it. The
physiology is fascinating, and it's
true. As we've gone over, yes, the
calories in your nutrition labels are
not going to be accurate to the calories
absorbed in the intestines as nutrients.
So, here's my advice.
Chuck it. I mean that earnestly. I don't
worry about any of that stuff when I
consider my own nutrition. If you're a
calorie counter like me, then keep using
the nutrition labels as your guide. Why?
Because regardless of what happens
inside your body, they still offer an
excellent foundation to adjust your
behavior accordingly. If I eat 2500
calories at my mouth, but only 1,900
calories get absorbed at a calorie
capable nutrients in my intestines, then
I'll eventually see that reflected in my
energy levels, my weight, my waist
measurements, and more. So without
knowing the amount that I'm actually
absorbing, I can change my behavior by
simply eating more if I want to gain
weight or stop weight loss or I can eat
less if I want to lose weight even more.
I don't care what my body does because
the actions to change it one way or
another are identical to if I knew the
exact calorie consumption in my
intestines. Now I'm focusing on
calories, but we also don't have to
focus on calories. We can focus on
nutrients or foods as a whole. More or
less of particular foods will also work.
If you're not a calorie counter like me,
then simply focus on foods that raise or
reduce your satiety depending on your
goals. Proteins tend to be more
satiating. Uh so deemphasize them if you
want to gain weight and emphasize them
if you want to lose weight. Then as you
track your progress through your body
measurements, journaling, whatever you
choose, you simply crank it up or you
crank it down. Like I said, all this
physiology and biochemistry is
fascinating, but we only really have a
limited number of levers that we can
pull that actually cause change at the
body level. So instead of worrying about
the specific foods blocking absorption
or what have you, just focus on moving
the totality of your diet in a direction
and make sure to measure on a regular
basis to get feedback on if your diet is
serving your direction or not. There's
plenty more I could say as you've heard
me say a few times now, but instead of
worrying about the tiny things, just
ignore it all and focus on the big
things. How do I feel? Is my body
performing or changing the way that I
want? How can I increase my total
protein or total fat or total fiber or
whatever you want? Those are the more
actionable questions and points. Not
being hyperfocused on the fact that you
ate viscous fiber with your omelette.
Therefore, you should only count 88% of
your calories from the omelette because
you predict that fiber will block 12%
from being absorbed.
Instead, you would eat like you normally
do. And if after 2 weeks your
measurements come back the same,
although you wanted them to change, you
just crank it up or crank it down in
some aspect of your overall nutrition,
like eating a bit more fiber with that
omelette or eating a smaller omelette.
You do those adjustments consistently,
your body will respond and you will have
worried about none of the tiny details.
Anyway, speaking of those details,
what's the hit rate on Dr. Listik's
points? Well, overall a lot of good
points like the importance of blood
sugar or the fact that our absorbed
calories are different from our eaten
calories for many outlined reasons.
However, there were also some
exaggerations and some incorrect
information like the addict
addictiveness of fructose or trans fats
not being able to be metabolized. One,
calories in versus calories out, while
explained simplistically
has a lot more complexity behind the
scenes considering hormones, impact of
specific nutrients, metabolic effects,
and more. Two, yes, for the last time,
calories on a nutrition label do not
necessarily reflect the amount that's
actually absorbed. For example, some
fibers can block or change nutrient
absorption. Three, amino acids in
proteins yield different amounts of
energy depending on the amino acid.
Applicably, it's not something to worry
about. Number four, omega-3 fats are
related to better health outcomes
generally, and industrial trans fats are
related to worse health outcomes.
However, they are both capable of being
metabolized by our body. Number five,
glucose is critical to life. from our
brain metabolism to acting as a
signaling molecule within our cells and
between our cells. Number six, fructose
is unlikely to be highly addictive, but
it also isn't necessary to consume.
However, some foods that contain
fructose, like fruit, are related to
better health outcomes because of the
other nutrients that come along with
fructose. Even if fructose in isolation
or close to it, like in soft drinks, is
generally still neutral or harmful to
health. Now, I'll get out of your hair
now, but if you're interested in another
centerfuge episode, check this video out
right here. Thanks for tuning in for
another episode. I'll catch you in the
next one. And I have to get my fructose
fixed now. Bye.